Finding Aid for Leroy Waterman Papers 1887-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Leroy Waterman Papers 1887-1972
Waterman, Leroy, 1875-1972.
5 linear feet
Bible scholar and translator, professor of Semitics at the University of Michigan; papers include correspondence, diaries, lectures and essays, archaeological expedition field notes and reports, and professional organization files.
86252 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Waterman's daughter, Mrs. Dorothea Ragland and came to the library in 1972. Donor no. 5277
The collection is open for research.
Leroy Waterman, a distinguished Bible scholar, translator and archaeologist, and an author of several books and many articles based on his archaeological and linguistic research, was a professor of Semitics at the University of Michigan from 1915 to 1945. He was born in Pierpont, Ohio, July 4, 1875, the son of Hadley Alpha and Louisa (Lombard) Waterman. He received his preliminary education at public schools in Pierpont, and at New Lyme Institute, New Lyme, Ohio. He graduated from Hillsdale College with a B.A. in 1898 and B.D. in 1900. He then studied at Oxford University (1900-02), the University of Berlin in (1906-07), and the University of Chicago where he received his Ph.D. degree in 1912.
During this same period of training, Waterman also taught, as a professor of Hebrew language and literature at the Divinity School of Hillsdale College from 1902 to 1910 and as a Fellow at the University of Chicago from 1910 to 1912. After receiving his doctorate, Waterman became a professor of the Old Testament and the history of religion at Meadville (Pa.) Theological School in 1913, and two years later joined the University of Michigan as head of the Department of Semitics, which later became the Department of Oriental Languages and Literatures. He remained at the U-M until his retirement as professor emeritus in 1945.
A distinguished Biblical scholar, Waterman, during the years 1922-27, was one of five members of the translation committee of the University of Chicago, whose work resulted in The Bible: An American Translation, sometimes called the Chicago Bible; and during 1938-52 he was a member of a committee of 31 scholars appointed by the National Council of Churches of Christ in America, which produced the Revised Standard Version of the Bible in 1952.
He served as the annual professor at the American School of Oriental Research, Baghdad, Iraq in 1928-29, and was director of the Mesopotamian archaeological expedition at Tel-Umar, twenty-five miles south of Baghdad near the Tigris river, sponsored by the University of Michigan, the Toledo (Ohio) Museum of Art, and the Cleveland (Ohio) Art Museum from 1928 to 1931. Waterman began the excavation of the ancient city of Seleucia, having located the site through his study of ancient writings and the use of aerial photos of an area of mounds in the desert. As director of the expedition for the first five seasons he established the site of the city, its general plan and architecture, and learned a great many new facts about the life of the times. Selucia, a city of 600,000 inhabitants, was the greatest city outside of Greece except for Alexandria. It was founded by Seleucus, a general of Alexander the Great. Some Parthian objects were discovered first, evidences of a later civilization, a mixture of Persian and Greek. Then a portion of a palace was excavated, and some very beautiful jewelry was found as well as pottery, coins, figurines, seals and other artifacts. Many bricks with the stamp of Nebuchadnezzar were found in the area. The results of the five seasons' work were published in the Preliminary Report Upon the Excavations at Tel Umar, Iraq (University of Michigan Press 1931) and the Second Preliminary Report (1933).
Waterman was also director of an archaeological expedition at Sepphoris, Galilee, near Nazareth during the summer of 1931 sponsored by the University of Michigan. Remains of a Roman theatre and an early Christian church were found, together with an aqueduct tunnel, pottery, coins, and numerous household objects of bone, and bronze, gold and iron jewelry. One objective of this project was to find materials that would enrich our knowledge of the life and times of Jesus. The results were published in the Preliminary Report of the University of Michigan at Sepphoris, Palestine (University, of Michigan Press, 1931).
In addition, Waterman also lectured for the University of Michigan Extension Service in Detroit, Grand Rapids, and Ann Arbor during the period of 1945-65, and was a teacher of Bible courses at the First Baptist and the First Methodist churches in Ann Arbor during 1961-71.
His scholarly works included editing volume XIV of R.F. Harper's Assyrian and Babylonian Letters (1912), and translating Some Koujunjik Letters and Related Texts (1912), and Business Documents of the Hammurabi Period (1916) and The Royal Correspondence of the Assyrian Empire, consisting of four volumes (1930).
Professor Waterman's particular interest was in the Old Testament and its extension into the New. His studies and research in this field together with his intense interest in current events led to the publication of the following books: Religion Faces the World Crisis (1943), The Religion of Jesus (1952), The Historical Jesus: Hope of Mankind (1955), Forerunners of Jesus (1959), Religion's Role in Tomorrow's World (1963), and The Christian Objective (1969). He also published a translation and interpretation of the Song of Songs (1948) and contributed numerous articles to various religious and scholarly journals.
Professor Waterman received an honorary D. Litt. degree from Hillsdale College in 1925 and an Honorary D.D. degree from Butler University in 1961. He was a member of the American Association for the Advancement of Science; the American Oriental Society, 1915 - Life member, annual president, 1936; National Association of Biblical Instructors, 1915; Royal Asiatic Society; Society of Biblical Literature and Exegesis (president, 1946); Society for Old Testament Study; Research Club of the University of Michigan; the University Club of Ann Arbor; and the Michigan Council of Churches and Christian Education, (president, 1937-42).
Leroy Waterman was married in Hillsdale, Michigan on July 24, 1906 to Mabelle Alice Walrath, daughter of Joseph Harvey and Lydia (Mount) Walrath of that city where her father was a Baptist minister. They had two children: Dorothea Lydia, who married George Ragland, Jr., and Donald Leroy (deceased 1931). Dr. Waterman died in Ann Arbor, Michigan on May 9, 1972.
The papers of Leroy Waterman (1875-1972) consist of five linear feet of correspondence, diaries, lecture notes, research notes, speeches, essays, photographs, news clippings, and other materials. The collection has been arranged into seven series: Biographical/personal; Correspondence; Diaries; Lectures, Essays, Speeches, Publications; Archaeological Expeditions; Organizational Affiliations; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Archaeology.; Bible--Versions.; Churchman.; Egypt.; Hillsdale College.; Iraq.; Michigan Council of Churches and Christian Education.; Michigan School of Religion.; Palestine.; University of Michigan--Archaeological expeditions.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Semitics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Antiquities.; Archaeological sites--Iraq.; Archaeological sites--Israel.; Archaeology.; Iraq--Archaeological sites.; Israel--Archaeological sites.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Scientific expeditions.; Waterman, Leroy, 1875-1972.
Contributors:
Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; McDowell, Robert H.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Biographical/family
  The Biographical/family series is small and consists mainly of a biographical sketch of Waterman written by his daughter, miscellaneous family and genealogical information, and photographs.
  - Biography of Leroy Waterman, by his daughter, Mrs. Dorothea Ragland (Box 1)
  - Sermon about Leroy Waterman by Rev. Edward J. Bottum 1970 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous biographical materials (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clipping file, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Booklet of correspondence on occasion of 90th birthday celebration 1965 (Box 1)
  - Genealogical. materials (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence 1842-1869 (Box 1)
  - Family Photographs (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1887-1972
  The Correspondence series dates from 1887 to 1972 and relates to most phases of Waterman's professional life and interests. As director of archaeological excavations in Tel-Umar, Iraq (Seleucia) from 1927 to 1931 and in Sepphoris in 1931, Waterman wrote many letters to his wife and children containing descriptions of the digging and finds. Additional working files and reports from these expeditions have been placed into a separate series. Also in the Correspondence series are communications from the period of his service as president of the Michigan Council of Churches and Christian Education (1937-1941).
  - Undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1887-1894 (Box 1)
  - 1895-1899 (Box 1)
  - 1900-1910 (Box 1)
  - 1911-1913 (Box 1)
  - 1914 (Box 1)
  - 1915-1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920-1926 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1927 (Box 1)
  - August-September 1927 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1927 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1928 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1928 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1929 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1929 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1930 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1934 (Box 1)
  - 1935-1936 (Box 1)
  - January-October 1937 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1937 (Box 1)
  - January-May 1938 (Box 1)
  - June-August 1938 (Box 1)
  - September-December 1938 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1939 (Box 1)
  - March-December 1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941-1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1952 (Box 1)
  - 1953-1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1963 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1964 (Box 1)
  - August-October 1964 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1964 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1965 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1965 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1966 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1966 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1967 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
- Diaries 1897-1964
  The Diaries series dates from 1897 to 1964. Waterman was a disciplined diarist writings with very few gaps for a period of nearly seventy years. Unfortunately one of the gaps, though it is partially made up with some undated entries, falls in the period of his two great archaeological expeditions. The diaries consist of fairly brief entries about his day's activities.
  - 1897 (Box 2)
  - 1898 (Box 2)
  - 1899 (Box 2)
  - 1900 (Box 2)
  - 1901 (Box 2)
  - 1902 (Box 2)
  - 1903 (Box 2)
  - 1904 (Box 2)
  - 1905 (Box 2)
  - 1906, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - 1906-1907 (Box 2)
  - 1907 (Box 2)
  - 1908 (Box 2)
  - 1909 (Box 2)
  - 1910 (Box 2)
  - 1911 (Box 2)
  - 1913 (Box 2)
  - 1914 (Box 2)
  - 1915 (Box 2)
  - 1916 (Box 2)
  - 1917 (Box 2)
  - 1918 (Box 2)
  - 1919 (Box 2)
  - 1920 (Box 2)
  - 1921 (Box 2)
  - 1922 (Box 2)
  - 1923 (Box 2)
  - 1924 (Box 2)
  - 1925 (Box 2)
  - 1926 (Box 2)
  - 1927 (Box 2)
  - 1928 (Mrs. Waterman) (Box 2)
  - circa 1930 (Box 2)
  - circa 1932 (Box 2)
  - 1933 (Box 2)
  - 1934 (Box 2)
  - 1935 (Box 2)
  - 1936 (Box 2)
  - 1937 (Box 2)
  - 1938 (Box 2)
  - 1939 (Box 2)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - 1942 (Box 2)
  - 1943 (Box 2)
  - 1944 (Box 2)
  - 1945 (Box 2)
  - 1946 (Box 2)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 2)
  - 1949 (Box 2)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - 1953 (Box 2)
  - 1955-1957 (Box 2)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - 1960 (Box 2)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - 1967 (Box 2)
- Lectures, essays, speeches, publications
  Lectures, Essays, Speeches, Publications consists of presentations given by Waterman to groups, his Guild class, and as part of the University of Michigan's Extension Service program. The topics covered relate mainly to studies of the Bible.
  - Volume of lectures: "Biblical Interpretations and Their Significance for Today" given 1963-1971 (Box 3)
  - Speeches
    - "Germany or Modern Imperialism," 1907 (Box 3)
    - "Survival of the Fittest, " 1910 (Box 3)
    - "Human Responsibility for the Kingdom of God," 1955 (Box 3)
    - "Flood Accounts and the Book of Genesis," 1967 (Box 3)
    - "Creative Leadership," undated (Box 3)
    - "The Mind of Christ," undated (Box 3)
  - Essays
    - "What We Owe to Greek Culture" (Box 3)
    - "The Reformation England" (Box 3)
    - "Evidence of Date in Psalms 90-150" (Box 3)
    - "Jesus in the Light of Prophecy" (Box 3)
    - "Doctrine of Atonement in Modern Thought" (Box 3)
    - "The Crown of Mastery" (Box 3)
    - "Higher Criticism." (Box 3)
    - "A New Method for Beginners in Hebrew" (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous speeches and essays, 14 folders (Box 3)
  - Published writings
    - Song of Songs translated and interpreted as a dramatic poem (1948) (Box 3)
    - Reprinted articles of LW, 3 folders (Box 3)
      (include reprint of dissertation and articles on archaeology)
  - Lecture notes, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Lecture notes, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - Lectures: U-M Broadcasting over WJR 1944 (Box 4)
  - Lecture notes, 3 volumes (Box 4)
    (include notes perhaps for Old Testament class at Hillsdale College, 1905)
- Archaeological Expeditions 1927-1936
  Archaeological Expeditions consists of materials accumulated from his Seleucia and Sepphoris expeditions, 1927-1936. These include field notes, maps, financial records, lists of objects found, published reports, and photographs.
  - Seleucia Expedition Files 1927-1936
    - Preliminary Report and Second Preliminary Report 1931, 1933 (Box 4)
    - Museum programs (Box 4)
    - Accounts and business documents (Box 4)
    - Lecture notes (Box 4)
    - Artifact locations and shipping records (Box 4)
    - List of Objects (Division lists) (Box 4)
    - Color Object drawings and descriptions (Box 4)
    - Photographs from Archaeological Expeditions (Box 4)
    - Photo Logs (Box 4)
  - Sepphoris Expedition Files 1931
    - Preliminary Report (Box 4)
    - Field Notes (Box 4)
    - Artifact locations (Box 4)
    - Maps (Box 4)
    - Photographs and photo lists (Box 4)
    - Photograph album from Archaeological Expeditions (Box 4)
  - General expedition materials
    - Waterman's passport and visa (Box 4)
    - Pamphlets, travel, etc., 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Photographs (book plates) (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous/unidentified photographs (Middle East) 1920s-1930s (Box 4)
    - Cuneiform tablet photos (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Publications of the Government of Iraq: Report on excavations for 1928/29-1931/32, 2 volumes (Box 4)
  - Papers written pertaining to expeditions
    - "Various Objects from Seleucia-on-the-Tigris, illustrating Daily Life in the City," by Samuel Yeivin 1933 (Box 4)
    - "Some Notes on the Work of the Michigan-Toledo-Cleaveland (sic) Expedition to Iraq" Second Report, Season 1930-1931 (Box 4)
    - "Vaulted Tombs, "by S. Yeivin (Box 4)
    - "Small Finds from Seleucia on the Tigris" by Samuel Yeivin, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings re archeological expeditions, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Organizational affiliations
  Organizational Affiliations is a series of files accumulated from Waterman's association with the Michigan Council of Churches and Christian Education, the Michigan School of Education and the Committee for the Revised Standard Version of the Bible. The bulk of this series concerns the years when Waterman was president of the Michigan Council of Churches and Christian Education, 1936 to 1940. Relatively few documents have been preserved concerning Waterman's contributions to the Committee for the Revised Standard Version of the Bible. Within the Correspondence series, there are several letters pertaining to the work of the Committee.
  - Michigan Council of Churches and Christian Education papers
    - Minutes and agendas 1936-1937 (Box 5)
    - Minutes and agendas 1938 (Box 5)
    - Minutes and agendas 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - Michigan School of Religion file
    - General, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Printed pamphlets (Box 5)
  - Committee for Revised Standard Version of the Bible
    - Minutes June 1970 (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings re publication of Revised Standard Version of the Bible (Box 5)
    - Speech on Revised Standard Version of the Bible, by Dorothea Waterman Ragland (daughter) (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series includes Waterman's notes taken while a student, some of his research materials on the Sumerian language, essays of his wife Mabelle, and accumulated speeches and articles by other scholars.
  - Research materials
    - Research notes on Sumerian language, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - Notes on the translation of Isaiah (Box 5)
  - Student notes
    - New Lyme Institute, Ohio 1892 (Box 5)
    - Oxford, England 1900, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - University of Chicago circa 1910-1912, 4 folders (Box 5)
      (mainly for classes taught by G. A. Smith and G. B. Foster)
  - Mabelle Walrath Waterman (wife) papers
    - Essays
      - "William Bryant" (Box 5)
      - "The Women of Germany" (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Notes on Waterman's Old Testament Course (Box 5)
    - Notes taken on class in Bible study circa 1950-1951 (Box 5)
  - Speeches, essays, and published materials of others
    - Essay, "Washington, Champion of Liberty" author unknown (Box 5)
    - Oration, "The Power that Elevates, "by J.H. Walrath (Box 5)
    - Speech, "Coming Against the Wind: Reformation II, " by George Mount (Box 5)
    - Inaugural Address of Prof. John Burgess at Friedrich Wilhelm University, Berlin 1907 (Box 5)
    - Paper, "Islam, "by Ameez Ali (Box 5)
    - Paper, "Catalogue of Coins of Sepphoris, " by Catharine S. Bunnell (Box 5)
    - Literarische Keilschrifttexte aus Assur. Edited by Erich Ebeling (Berlin: Akademie Verlag, 1953) (Box 5)
    - Journal articles, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Pamphlets concerning religious life at the University of Michigan (Box 5)
  - Reviews of Waterman's books (Box 5)
  - Class lists 1903-1923 (Box 5)
  - Church bulletins and programs (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)